<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of Nevv England published in anno Dom. 1637. And now reprinted.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2092A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831593</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831593</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36057</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63101)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36057)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2046:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of Nevv England published in anno Dom. 1637. And now reprinted.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint conjectured by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>New England --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:36057:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36057:1"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe of New ENGLAND Publiſhed in <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1637.</head>
            <head type="sub">And now reprinted.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ew <hi>England</hi> is a Countrey in <hi>America,</hi> Scitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within the Degrees of fortie, and fortie nine of Northerly Latitude, bordering South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſtward upon <hi>Maryland</hi> and <hi>Virginia,</hi> North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward upon <hi>Nova Francia,</hi> Northeaſtward up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Nova Scotia,</hi> and Southward upon the great Ocean, firſt called by the Spaniards, <hi>Mare del Nort</hi> (or the North Sea) not for its height ſo far Northerly, but in oppoſition of the Sea which is on the other ſide of that Continent, called the South ſea. The Sea coaſt thereof, from its Southernmoſt to <hi>Cape Codd,</hi> bearing Weſt ſouthweſt, and Eaſt Northeaſt; and from <hi>Cape Codd</hi> to <hi>Cape Croix,</hi> being infortie five Degrees odd minuts, and the utmoſt bounds of <hi>New-England</hi> Northward, lying Southweſt and Northeaſt. This Country, together with <hi>Nova Scotia,</hi> was formerly called
<hi>Norombega,</hi> which hath bin this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares diſcovered and poſſeſſed by the Engliſh, in right of the Crowne of <hi>England.</hi> This Land in the Superficies (the ſtore of Wood excepted) may be compared to this Kingdome. As for <hi>De-la-ware Bay</hi> to <hi>Cape Codd,</hi> being an indifferent low Land, is like to the ſhires of <hi>Eſſex Suffolke, Norfolke, Cambridge, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingdon, Lincolne;</hi> and from <hi>Cape Codd</hi> Eaſtward, more hilly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling <hi>Hampſhire, Dorceſter, Devon</hi> and <hi>Cornwall.</hi> As theſe two parts of the Country differ in forme, ſo they do in fertility; for that to the Weſtward of
<hi>Cape Codd,</hi> exceedeth the other to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:36057:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Eaſtward, as much in rich Soile as in levell; and withall, hath more large Marſhes upon the Sea coaſt, now ſubject to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation of high-tides howbeit, divers of them might be gained from the water (if ever the Planters ſhould undertake it) with far leſſe charge, than to make Tillable the like quantity of wood land, by reaſon the in-lets are but narrow, and bounded with aſcending grounds.</p>
            <p>2. The inner part of the Countrey conſiſteth moſt of <hi>Vpland,</hi> full of Woods, yet is ſo well furniſhed with fertile low Plaines and Vallies, that in croſſing the Woods, one ſhall hardly miſſe in three or foure myles of ſuch places, whereof ſome are very ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and delightfull, with cleere freſh Rivers or Brooks gliding through them; without Fenne or Bogge, and ſcarſe a ſhrub or buſh to hinder a Ploughs going; and commonly flanked or ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with woody Hills, whence a man may behold as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant proſpects (building, Tillage and Cartell excepted) as any in all <hi>England;</hi> wherein Planters may have choice enough of rich Earable land for many Generations. Thoſe Vallies and Marſhes upon the Sea Coaſt, beare Graſſe of a great length and thicknes, in ſome places ſo ranke, that it is above an Ell in height; which, though it be not at the firſt cutting ſo fine as our Engliſh Graſſe, yet is ſuch good Winter Fodder as that Cattell thrive well there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and the oftner it is mowed, the finer it groweth. The <hi>Vpland</hi> alſo in moſt places is ſufficient good land, producing Graſſe very thick, ſweet and timely, eſpecially where the Indians have cleared any quantity of ground to plant their Corne in, and afterwards quitted it for new choiſe. The ſoile in generall is of diverſe ſorts. The Vallies and Marſhes are for the moſt part a fat black Mould, ſaving in ſome places a kind of a loamie Clay, whereof the Planters make Brickes, Tiles, and earthen Veſſells. The <hi>Vpland</hi> is either a Gravell Sandy, or ſomewhat ſtronger in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to a Clay ground, each being very beneficiall to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of a painfull Husbandman.</p>
            <p>3. That Country is ſtored with as great and good choice of all forts of timber as any one land in the knowne world; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three kinds of Oake, each excelling the other for particular uſes, with plenty of all kindes of trees that <hi>England</hi> affords; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many other kinds of Wood very uſefull for this Kingdom, which it ſelfe yeeldeth not; as Spruce, Firre, and Deale of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary growth, for Maſts, Yards and Plankes; out of which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36057:2"/> Wood may bee extracted, Pitch, Tarre, Rozin and Turpintine. Likewiſe, Pine trees, Cedar, Cipres, Saſſaphras, with the Sumack, which is very good for Dyers and Tanners; out of this Sumack and Shee-Cedar iſſueth ſweet Gums, much uſed for perfumes. All thoſe that work in Wood, do find thoſe trees for goodneſſe very anſwerable to their deſires. There be ſeverall kinds of trees that be are fruit, as Wallnut Cheſtnut, Haſelnut trees and divers ſorts of Plumbe trees; with infinite ſtore of Vines that beare Grapes in great cluſters, and as big many of them, as Musket bullets; which ſome of the Inhabitants, both Engliſh and Dutch, have tranſplanted, who are of opinion, by what they have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy tried, that with dreſſing and pruning of them, they will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make as good Wines as any part of
<hi>France.</hi> All the Woods over, there be Cheſtnuts, Wallnuts Haſelnuts, Currance, Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, Rasberries, Gooſeberries, Hurtleberries, Hawes, with many other kindes of fruit and roots which are excellent food for Hogges, and cauſeth them to increaſe wonderfull in growth and profit.</p>
            <p>4. That Earth fructifieth exceedingly all kinds of Engliſh and Indian Corne, and the Planters doe find by experience, that it beareth as great crops, and more increaſe than in any part of this Kingdom: Yet therebe divers experienced Farmers which doe neglect our Engliſh Beanes and Peaſe, and ſow thoſe of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> preferring them before the other, for goodnes of taſt and profit. But the product of <hi>Indian</hi> Wheat, which is a good food, ſurpaſſeth all other graine; for 100. and 50. and 200. is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the increaſe thereof: And there be ſome of good credit now in this Kingdome who have affirmed, that they had above 300. fold. The worth of that Land is manifeſtly confirmed, in that it is an uſuall courſe with thoſe Farmers (upon the firſt cutting up of their ground) to ſow either Hempe or
<hi>Indian</hi> Wheate to correct the ranckneſſe of it, as being too ſtrong for any other graine: there bee alſo Hempe and Flax that groweth natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſomwhat ſhorter and ſlenderer then ours in <hi>England,</hi> but much finer and ſtronger, whereof the <hi>Indians</hi> make Cords and Nets, which may prove in time a great ſtaple commodity for Cordadge Canvas, and other ſorts of finer linnen. Likewiſe that Country affordethh naturally diverſity of medecinable Roots, Herbs, and Flowers, ſome of them being very beautifull and fragrant, with other kinds wholſome and good for ſawce and ſallads, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36057:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> of Strawberries throughout the fields, larger and as good as any Garden Strawberries in <hi>England:</hi> For all kinds of Garden Roots and Herbs that are planted or ſowed they proſper marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous well, and are very uſefull for the Plantors. Moreover the ground is ſo rich, and the climate ſo ſeaſonable, that it would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford as good Woad, Madder, Rape and Safron, as in any land where they are now growing.</p>
            <p>5. There may be had all Materials for Buildings, whether Forts, Caſtles, Churches, Houſes, or any other Structures, as Free-ſtone, Smooth ſtone, and Marble ſlats for covering, Lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone for morter and plaiſtering, with choiſe Timber, and all other appurtenances fit for finiſhing.</p>
            <p>Some affirme, that there be divers ſorts of Mines, but little that I know of, hath bin as yet found, excepting Black-lead and Iron-ſtone of ſeverall kinds, which may in time move the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Planters to ſet up Iron works, having Wood and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſaries fit to maintaine them for many ſucceeding ages; and may prove a ſpeciall meanes to preſerve the Woods here in <hi>England.</hi> Good ſalt hath bin there found, candied by the Sun upon the ſides of the Rocks, where high ſpring Tides hath left any quantity of ſalt water, inſomuch, that it is aſſuredly knowne, there might be made as good ſalt in many places to the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Cape Codd,</hi> as in any part of <hi>France.</hi> Likewiſe for Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſhes, there is no Land where more may be made, nor at leſſe charge, for the Planters might therewith ſupply this Kingdome yearly with more then can be uſed, out of the ſuperfluous Woods they have about their Plantations.</p>
            <p>6. There are alſo many faire Lakes (which are the heads of all or moſt of the principall Rivers of the Country) ſtored with good choice of dainty freſh Fiſh, where the Salvages take their Beavers Otters, and other Furres; but the Planters have not yet diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in all that continent neere <hi>Virginia</hi> and <hi>New England,</hi> any worthy of particular mention but three. The one is the Lake St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> in the Weſt end of <hi>New England,</hi> which is
60. leagues in length, and 30. Leagues broad, but extendeth it ſelfe ſo farre weſterly, that I could not inſert it in this Mapp. Another Lake there is ſixteen leagues to the weſtward of this quite out of the bounds of <hi>New England,</hi> not expreſt here at all, named by the
<hi>French La Merdulce,</hi> in Engliſh the freſh Sea. This Lake is 160. leagues long, and 60. in bredth, two great fluxes of water are found
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36057:3"/> to goe out of this large Ciſterne; the greater falleth off at the Weſt part of it, and runneth Weſterly within the ſpace of fifteen leagues into a Bay of ſalt water, which muſt needs bee an Arme of the South Sea. The other Eaſtward &amp; looſeth it ſelfe into Lake St. <hi>Lew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>is.</hi> The third is the Lake of <hi>Hierocoyis,</hi> lying in the body of
<hi>New-England,</hi> the length thereof being 40 Leagues and the bredth 80. miles. As the Lakes of that Country are vaſt and numerous, ſo they produce many goodly Rivers, ſome of them far bigger then any in this our <hi>Brittaine,</hi> of which <hi>Canada</hi> is the greateſt, iſſuing out of that great Lake St. <hi>Lewis:</hi> And taking its courſe all along the North part of <hi>New England,</hi> divideth it from <hi>Nova Francia,</hi> and disburtheneth it ſelfe in the great Bay Northeaſtward of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va Scotia.</hi> The ſecond is <hi>Mauritius River,</hi> ſo called by the Dutch, but by the Engliſh, <hi>Hudſons River,</hi> who firſt diſcovered it: This River hath divers branches, the chiefe of which, commeth out of the Lake
<hi>Hieroquoyis,</hi> as the Indians and Dutch among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves report, but deſcribe it not ſo [as it is ſuppoſed] leſt the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſhould find out by that meanes a way to the Lake, and ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of their great Beaver trade; it floweth forty leagues into the land, and is Navigable divers leagues higher, running all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>New England,</hi> and is received into <hi>Sandt</hi> or <hi>Manahatas Bay,</hi> a league and a halfe from the prime Plantation of the Dutch, in the latitude of forty degrees, and thirty ſix minutes. The third is <hi>Den Suidt River,</hi> or ſouth River, which parteth <hi>New England</hi> from <hi>Virginia</hi> and
<hi>Mary Land,</hi> being Navigable five and thirty leagues at leaſt. Many are of oppinion upon good probabilities, that this and <hi>Patowmack</hi> a River, which runneth thorough part of
<hi>Virginia</hi> and <hi>Maryland</hi> into the Sea at <hi>Cheſapeacke</hi> Bay] de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend both out of the Lake <hi>St. Lewis.</hi> The fourth is <hi>St. Croix</hi> River, which diſtinguiſheth <hi>New England,</hi> from <hi>Nova Scotia.</hi> There bee many other Navigable Rivers, as <hi>Merimack Sagadahock, Conecte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, Champloiones River,</hi> and others which would be too tedious to diſcovrſe of particularly: For Brooks and ſprings of ſweet water, there be ſo many, that Planters whereſoever they ſeat them ſelves, need not feare ſcarcity of water in the greateſt drought for any uſe. Sea-men that frequent that Country commend it for diverſity of good Harbours ſo that whenceſoever the wind blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, they have one or other to put into for ſafe-guard: For the Coaſt being full of Ilands and broken land, have many openings, which make the Chanels deepe and narrow, between which Ilands
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36057:4"/> and the maine land, lie the moſt and beſt Harbours which are ſheltred on the ſhore ſide with high Cliffs, Woods, or both; and towards the Sea with Ilands or Head-lands, which break the ways of that ſwelling Sea, ſo that the tides come in where the Shipps ride ſo calme that they are hardly ſenſible of any ſtorm. Another great commodity of theſe Harbours is, that Ships may ride there without danger of Worm-eating, which they cannot do unleſſe they be ſheathed, in <hi>Virginia, Florida,</hi> &amp; further to the Southward. The raggednes of the Coaſt, and ſtraight entrance into the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are partly fortified by Nature, in that there be few of them ſo broad, but an ordinary caſt peece will execute from one Bank to another, where with a little Art may bee raiſed (as they have done in ſeverall places) ſuch ſtrong works as will bee able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the power of an invading Enemy.</p>
            <p>7. All Engliſh and Spaniſh Cattle which were tranſported thither, grow larger, and yeeld more profit than thoſe of the ſame kind whence they came; and which is more, Dutch beaſts which were carried out of a fatter Soile then ours, do with bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there, become larger in ſize then otherwiſe, and none of them have bin hitherto ſubject to thoſe diſeaſes incident to Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in this Land: But for their Poultry, comparing the number of thoſe Planters in Families and Eſtates with the Inhabitants of this Country, they will be found better provided. The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that is made by the Planters of their Cattle, Corne and other commodities which the Land affords them is great, conſidering what good eſtates divers induſtrious men have attained unto in a ſhort time, out of ſmall beginnings.</p>
            <p>8. There are of the Native Beaſts both ravenous and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious; The Ravenous are Beares, Wolves, Luſerans or Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Foxes, Squunks, Ferrets, and wild Dogs, very like the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Curs of <hi>England,</hi> which the <hi>Salguages</hi> doe take and tame when they are young to follow them who never bark; but againſt rain or foule weather, will then ſet themſelves to howle, making a moſt hideous yelling noiſe: The beaſts that are commodious be profitable two wayes, either for food or furs. For Furs, ſuch are Beavers, Otters, Minks, Rackoons, Muſquaſh, Sables, and others. There have bin Bears, black Wolves and Foxes taken, whoſe caſes are of great eſteem here in <hi>England:</hi> the beaſts for food are Elks, Deer of two kinds, Hares and Rabbets: the beare and Squunk alſo are eſteemed by the Planters little inferiour to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36057:4"/> Veale and Lambe: For thoſe Deere, the leſſer of them are a kinde of Red Deere, but not altogether ſo bigg and large as ours, who never beat themſelves ſo low at rut, but that they will be fat all the winter, and are as good Veniſon as any in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: theſe have their brow and beam antlers, broaches, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and as many ſtarts upon their heads, as our Engliſh Deer, but grow more compaſt and forward: the other is as large as an Oxe, called a Mooſe, headed ſomwhat like a Buck with broad palms, but much wider then our Red or fallow Deer; theſe Moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are heavy ſlow beaſts, which frequent the low rank grounds to feed upon long graſſe, by reaſon their fore feet are longer then their hinder feet, whoſe fleſh is of a courſe big grain, &amp; eats like unto Beefe. Both theſe kind of Deer bring ordinarily 3. Calves at a fall and timelier then our engliſh Deer by 2. months: there be many kinds of ſea and land Fowle, wherof ſome may be made fit for recreation, others for ſuſtenance, with a third kind good for neither; as Eagles, Gripes, Ravens, Cormorants, and Crows: For ſports you have Faulcons, Lanners, Goſhawks, and others for food, Turkies, Grouces, Patridges, Cranes, wild Swans, wild Geeſe of 3. kinds, Ducks, Widgins, Teales, Herons, fea and Land Larks, with many others in greater plenty by far then in theſe Countries, with ſeverall ſinging Birds ſtrang to us, that are very glorious to the eye for diverſity of colours. But there is a Fowle, which ſome that write of them call Pidgeons, whoſe colour is like to the Turtle, and tayled like to a Magpy, otherwiſe for their ſhape and flying, I ſhould rather thinke them to bee a kind of Stock-Doves, which Fowle in <hi>October,</hi> fly in ſuch flocks, that I have ſeene the sky darkned with them; as if it had bin o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-caſt with a cloud, all flying from the North South-ward to ſome hotter Region, where they continue untill the ſpring, and then do return to build and breed towards <hi>Nova Scotia,</hi> in a more temperate clymate for the ſummer.</p>
            <p>9. As that Sea which flanketh the Coaſt of <hi>New England,</hi> is the moſt ſpacious in the world, ſo it affordeth the greateſt ſtore and moſt variety of fiſh, for neere to
<hi>De-la-ware Bay</hi> there are more Whales and Grampaſſes then in <hi>Groinland;</hi> and all the Coaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long there are great abundance of <hi>Salmon,</hi> Sturgion, Turbut, Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, Baſſe, Mackerill, Thornbacke, Hake, Herrings, Shads, Scules, Eales, Lampries, Smelts, and all other kinds taken in our Engliſh ſeas, with many others, not knowne by any names to our Nation:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36057:5"/> As for <hi>Codd,</hi> the fiſhing voyages made yearely out of <hi>England</hi> for that purpoſe, will ſufficiently prove their plenty, and withall there is neither Bay nor Creek, but is as full of Lobſters, Oyſters, Scal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops, Crabs, Cockles, Praunes, Clammes, Muſſels, Perewinkles, &amp;c. So that a Boy may go into divers places on the water ſide, and take more in one houre than will dine eight or ten Men.</p>
            <p>10. Touching the Climate; That Country is placed in the principall part of the temperate
<hi>Zone,</hi> where being ten Degrees neerer the <hi>Equinoctiall</hi> than this Land; the
<hi>Ayre</hi> is better dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, which maketh a very ſerene and freſh Skie: So that <hi>New England</hi> is generally preferred before this land for healthfulnes, ſympathizing better then our Engliſh Nation; more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, ſuch as are troubled with any Cold, Rhumaticke or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholcke diſtemperatures; for the temper of that Climate is ſomewhat hotter then is ordinary here in Summer, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what colder in the Winter, yet the Summer is not ſo hot, but men indure the heat to labour in; nor the Winter ſo cold, but with moderate ſtirring they may brook the ſharpeſt ayre a whole day; but for the ſpring and Autumne, they are very tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and pleaſant. I need not writ much concerning the length of dayes and nights, for there is no Intelligent Traveller but knoweth the nearer a Country is to the <hi>Equinoctiall,</hi> there the more equall both nights and dayes are in Winter and ſummer; ſo that in the ſouth part of
<hi>New England,</hi> the dayes are two houres and a halfe ſhorter in Summer than in this Kingdome, and as much longer in the Winter.</p>
            <p>11. There be three Nations beſides the Indians who inhabit that Country, namely, French, Engliſh, and Dutch: the French are the moſt Northerly Plantation, being in number about two hundred, and the laſt of the three that poſſeſſed any part of the Land, they are ſet downe in a place called <hi>Penobſcot,</hi> where they have erected a Fort and neceſſary buildings, but apply themſelves hitherto, more to the trad of <hi>Beaver,</hi> than to Fiſhing or prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Land to eſtabliſh a Plantation.</p>
            <p>12. The next are the Engliſh who are thought to be no leſſe than 30000. perſons, whoſe plantations are all (excepting one) to the Northward of <hi>Cape Codd;</hi> but becauſe there be of them two diſtinct Collonies, the one at <hi>New Plymouth,</hi> the other at the
<hi>Maſachuſets Bay,</hi> who went not over together, nor hold their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36057:5"/> eſtates by the ſame grant; I thought good [for the Readers bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter information] to ſpeak ſomewhat of them ſeverally. The firſt that came into the Land, are thoſe of <hi>New Plymouth,</hi> who went over from <hi>Amsterdam</hi> and <hi>Leiden</hi> in
<hi>Holland,</hi> and were ſet out at the charge of divers Marchants for the ſouth part of
<hi>Virginia:</hi> but being croſs'd in their voyage by contrary winds and ſtormes were forced to land in <hi>New England,</hi> much weather beaten and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced in their Proviſion; where, through want of meanes to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their purpoſe, did continue untill they ſent their Maſters word of this croſſe fortune, which was ſoone diſpatched, deſiring a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſupply of Neceſſaries, and a Direction what they ſhould fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe. In the meane time, they ſought out the beſt helpes that that Country could afford for lively-hood, having no Proviſion but what they got with labour and danger, nor then ſufficient to content Nature; yet all of them with much hardneſſe and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſuſtained the want of this rude Deſart, expecting ſome reliefe to come to them, but this bad and unexpected newes tooke off the edge of the Adventurers hopes, ſo that they concluded, rather then to hazard any more money for their ſecond tranſportation, to loſe what was already expended. Nevertheleſſe, they inployed their wits and hands ſome to build houſes, others to go abroad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Country to ſeek what they could finde for profit; and after much ſearch, happily hapned upon ſome trade for <hi>Beaver</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Furres, which they did ſo diligently follow, that within a ſhort time they had not only quitted themſelves from the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition they were lately in, but began to raiſe ſome bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and to conceive a good hope of a growing and continuing gaine, which in a ſhort time ſuited their expectation. For, whereas they were at that time but covenant Servants to the Marchants did within the round of eighteen months or two yeares; but out their Freedome (as I take it for eighteen hundred pounds) paying them by two hundred pounds a yeare; but within a yeare or two after, they came to another compoſition, which was, That if the Marchants would abate part of the ſumme agreed upon, they would diſcharge all in one payment, which was effected to the contentment of both parties. This proſperous ſucceſſe of theirs being knowne here in
<hi>England,</hi> perſwaded in many ſuch a good oppinion of that Country that they reſolved to adventure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and eſtates into thoſe parts, in hopes of the like fortune,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36057:6"/> for not long after, there went over many who joyned with them and more do ſtill ſo that they are now growne to a great number of Planters, and of good eſtates. But they follow the Trade of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> with that greedineſſe by reaſon of preſent profit] that they do not apply themſelves ſo much to cleare and fence grounds for til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage as other Planters, whereby the Inhabitants might be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the fruit of Husbandry, and the brood of Cattell increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which indeed is the beſt and ſureſt foundation of a ſetled Colonie.</p>
            <p>13. The other Plantation is that of the <hi>Maſachuſetts Bay,</hi> who went over well provided with all neceſſaries, intending to raiſe themſelves new eſtates in that Country. The better ſort of them being Gentlemen of good eſtates and reputation here in
<hi>England:</hi> the reſt were very induſtrious and painfull, who brought over either competent meanes to put themſelves into a thriving courſe, or had good Occupations and Trades, wherby they might live upon the accommodations of the Country: And withall, are now very deſirous to have ſuch a Government ſetled by the Kings Authority, that will ſubject all of them to the Laws of this Land, whereby the abuſes of ſuch as are refrectory may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed and corrected and the obedience of the reſt cheriſhed and defended. This Plantation hath bin very ſucceſſefull and ate al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready growne ſo numerous, that they are diſperſed throughout the Sea-coaſt of this Bay, above fifty miles in compaſſe: In ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places whereof, they have built Forts of good ſtrength, with diverſe Townes and villages which are able to intertain ſuch as come over, with houſe-room and other refreſhings, while they build and make Proviſion upon their owne lots; and whereas ſome Scituations would not afford them arrable grounds enough neere the towns, they have found out convenient places further in the Country for tillage and Meadowing, where they have good Farms. Their chiefe imployments hitherto have bin Husbandry, trading for <hi>Beaver,</hi> and fiſhing: For their husbandry, they brought that to ſo good a perfection, that all of them who have lived there any reaſonable time, have ſufficient to maintaine their Families out of their ſtocks in Corn and Cattell: For their
<hi>Beaver</hi> trade, it hath continued very beneficiall unto them a good while after their firſt comming over but it ſoone decaied ſithence there went ſo many Planters with trucking commodities, that all of them traded promiſcuouſly, reſpectleſſe of the manner and rates the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36057:6"/> Planters uſed, which was not to exceed a certain proportion; and this corruption ſtill gaining upon their covetouſneſſe, have brought it now to this paſſe, that ſo ſoon as they can diſcrie any <hi>Salvages</hi> comming towards their Plantations with Fur, they will all flock about them, one out-bidding another while there is any materiall gaine, ſo that they can hardly get two <hi>Beavers</hi> for that commodity t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey exchanged for ten or twelve.</p>
            <p>14. And for their fiſhing, they made Weres in many places where the tides leave ſo much fiſh, that they doe not only ſerve all the Plantations therewith throughout the Yeare, but are forced (and that for a good purpoſe) to carry the overplus to fatten their Land with, leſt thoſe great Shoales ſhould break, or choake up the VVeres. But the wealth that the Planters might get by ſetting up the trade of fiſhing (did they effectually go in hand therewith) may bee conceived, by comparing that Coaſt with other fiſhing places; for it is well knowne that it equalizeth <hi>Groin-land</hi> for VVhales and Grampaſſes. The Iriſh and North Sea for Herring and ſalt fiſh. The Baltick ſea for Sturgion and Muller. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all doth exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l <hi>New-found-land,</hi> fiſhing for
<hi>Poore-John,</hi> in that the fiſh is larger and the ſeaſon ſooner by above two moneths, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may bee at their Markets in their Ilands. <hi>Italy, Spaine</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> before he others have their Fiſh a ſhipboard in <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found-land,</hi> and will ſell their fiſh at a greater price. Furthermore, they have in divers reſpects, the advantage of our
<hi>New-found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Fiſhermen (who are at a great charge in buying of ſalt ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of time and Victualls before they arrive at their fiſhing place) by reaſon they are at hand, and may in a ſhort time fit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with all proviſion for that work. But thoſe Planters (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting ſome particular men who built a few ſhipps for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) have bin hitherto hindred by their Land imployments, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will there bee much good done before they make a generall ſtocke, and incorporate themſelves into one body; which being wiſely managed may in a few years raiſe them to great eſtats, and make them maſters of ſuch a Navall power as will be able to doe the King ſervice and defend their own Country.</p>
            <p>15. What I have hitherto written of <hi>New England,</hi> is upon the matter generall now I purpoſe to write ſomwhat in particular; concerning a part of the Country which lieth between
<hi>Delaware Bay,</hi> and <hi>Cape Codd,</hi> that is more than halfe the land in extent, though not in Degrees, by reaſon it beareth more Weſterly then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36057:7"/> the other and that hath not bin formerly mentioned by any mans Relati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, but from <hi>Cape Codd</hi> Northeaſtward, Captaine <hi>Smith,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Woods</hi> have diſcourſed copiouſly of the ſeverall ſcituations and plantations as alſo of the manner, and profit of that Fiſhing, whoſe Bookes are now extant.</p>
            <p>16. The only Planters who poſſeſſed that Weſtern part of the Countrie excepting one ſmall Plantation of Engliſh upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Conectecute</hi>] are the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who firſt came into the land about the yeare 1622. and putting into <hi>Hudſons</hi> river (which they call <hi>Mauritius River</hi>) ſpent ſome time with the Indians in trading for Beaver, and took poſſeſſion of that place in their <hi>Weſt-India Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies</hi> name, who then imployed them, and afterwards returned into <hi>Holland,</hi> moving their Maſters with ſome experimentall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to be at the charge of tranſporting a Colony thither, which the Company undertooke, For in the yeare following they ſet out a ſhip for the ſame River, with ſome 60 Planters furniſhed with trucking Commodities, and all neceſſaries for a twelve-moneth, who upon their firſt landing ſearched all the places neere the Sea ſide for a commodious Scituation, at laſt choſe <hi>Manahatas Iland</hi> for two reaſons, one reſpecting a good Harbor, the other for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of commerce with the Indians. This Iland is ten leagues in compaſſe, and a league and a halfe broad or thereabouts, at the South part whereof, they raiſed a ſtrong Fort, with 4. compleat Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks, upon which they have 20 caſt Pieces mounted: neere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this Fort live all the Planters that are Artifficers, but their
<hi>Boores</hi> diſperſe themſelves farther Northward into the Iland where it is more fertile than about the Plantation, with in 4 or 5. miles Eaſtward of this place, is a large plaine of ten or twelve miles wide, which is very fit for Farmers to inhabit, but on the Weſt ſide it is more ruſte and hilly. There is another Iland a league and a halfe from this Plantation that is more fertile than <hi>Manahatas</hi> (which they called <hi>The States Iland</hi>) fronting Southward upon the Bay, at the Eaſt point thereof, we enter firſt into <hi>Mauritius</hi> River, being not above a Falcon ſhoot over where there might be a Fort made of ſuch conſequence, that would ſecure the whole Plantation from any danger of an invaſion: This Iland is ſome 9. leagues about, and the fitteſt place to be planted of any other neerer the Sea ſide, by reaſon of the great quantity of arrable land there is in it; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, of having Men at hand to reſiſt the enterance of an Enemy into that River.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:36057:7"/>17. Not long after their firſt comming into the land, they ſailed in a ſmall Veſſell 46 leagues up this River, and [finding there a far greater Trade than by the Sea coaſt planted another Colonie, and erected a little work in forme of a Redoubt, which they call <hi>Fort Aurania;</hi> but for their better ſecuring, they have caſt up ſince a high Trench about it, where there is 7 or 8 pieces of Ordnance mounted. The Banks of this River for divers leagues together thereabouts, is an exceeding fat Soyle, ſurpaſſing all that on the Sea coaſt, inſomuch that the Planters of <hi>Manahatas,</hi> when they have wrought their Cattle ſo weake that they are not able long to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, do uſe to ſend them to <hi>Fort Aurania,</hi> wherewith that rich feeding they recover their fleſh and ſtrength in a ſhort time, within a day and a halfe or two dayes journey at the furtheſt from this place, is the Lake
<hi>Hieroquoyis</hi> ſo famous for <hi>Beavers</hi> and <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> which maintaineth the greateſt part of the <hi>Bever</hi> trade in the <hi>French</hi> Plantation at <hi>Quibec,</hi> and alſo affordeth this Colonie more then they have in all their Factoris beſides. The
<hi>Dutch mens</hi> aime is, to get up and plant a Collony upon the Bank of this Lake, where they might with eaſe ingroſſe to themſelves moſt of that great and rich Trade, having a very advantagious helpe withall by their River to tranſport to, and from the Sea ſide a great way, though not up to it all proviſions neceſſary for their uſe and trade which if they could but compaſſe, would inable them in a ſhort time, but that only gaine, to plant and fortifie that part of the Land which they now hold ſo ſtrong, that they might make a powerfull reſiſtance againſt any forraigne invaſion. Part of the Dutch went from <hi>Manahatas</hi> foure yeares ſithence, and fettled another Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation upon the River <hi>Conectecute,</hi> which is held to be one of the beſt ſituations for Tillage in all the Country; but ſome Engliſh who came from the <hi>Maſachuſſets Bay,</hi> planted above them upon the ſame River, and do cut off their Trade for <hi>Beaver,</hi> ſo that they have little elſe to make profit of but their Husbandrie.</p>
            <p>18. In the yeare 1630. they ſet up a Plantation on the South ſide of <hi>De-la-ware Bay,</hi> and finding that ſoile very fertile, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to plant <hi>Tobacco,</hi> which if it had taken effect, would have much prejudiced the <hi>Virginians</hi> for the ſale of that commodity in the <hi>Netherlands</hi> and many other places; but the indiſcretion of that
<hi>Dutch</hi> Governour gave a wofull period to the Collony, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I will relate to forewarne others from the like folly. The cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> when they take poſſeſſion of any ſtrange
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36057:8"/> Land, is to faſten upon a tree the Arms of their Country, as they did in this place; but a ſimple <hi>Indian</hi> paſſing by eſpied it, and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of what it meant took it off and caried it away: which, when the <hi>Governour</hi> underſtood, was much incenſed therewith, holding it for a great affront, inſomuch, that when the Princes and chiefe of them came firſt into the Quarter, were laid hands on and examined upon his miſdemeanour; who pleaded, they knew not of it: nevertheles he threatned their lives, in caſe they would not bring in the Malefactor to anſwer it and in the mean time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained them for Priſoners: when the poor people ſaw themſelves in that exigent got the Offender to come in, thinking the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt not to deſerve death; but when the ſimple people under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood his danger, they offered a great ranſom for his life, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would, nor did ſatisfie this auſtere <hi>Iudge,</hi> but the poor <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> bloud: when this was done, the <hi>Salvages</hi> were diſcharged, who masked their diſcontent under a faire ſhew of friendſhip, frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Plantation as they had done with ſome trade or other; but within a while after, there came ſo many of them together, that they cut all the Planters throats in an inſtant, demoliſhed their Fort, and deſtroyed what elſe they had there, ſo this Plantation continued not much above a yeare.</p>
            <p>19. This Nation have a trade in the South-River, and the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roganſes Bay,</hi> whence they get from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>New Engl.</hi> and <hi>Virginia, 6000. Beavers</hi> in a yeare; and withall, have leſſer Boats that go into all the Creeks and Rivers between thoſe two places, where they glean all the trade of the Country; Inſomuch, that I believe, theſe people who are not above 700. in their ſeverall plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, do make a greater benefit of the
<hi>Beaver</hi> trade than all our Engliſh in <hi>New-England</hi> being 30000. They have made an experiment in <hi>Delaware Bay,</hi> of Whale fiſhing, but by reaſon of their ſlow preparation, came not ſo ſoon as the ſeaſon required; nevertheleſſe, they killed 2. or
3. and were confident of a great voyage had they come in time: for they report, that there is greater ſtore of ſuch fiſh than in <hi>Groinland.</hi> But upon that maſſacre the
<hi>Indians</hi> ſpoiled all their fiſhing craft, that they never followed that imployment afterwards. The Planters have built in <hi>Manahatas Iland</hi> many little Boats and Shallops, with divers Ships from 70. to 200. Tuns and upwards, and one of 700. Tuns, which was fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with as good Maſts and Yards as any come from the Eaſt Country; and they have Sailes, Cables, Cordage, and all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36057:8"/> fit for their ſetting out, for all other proviſion that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to a Collony; they are generally better ſtockt than any other Plantation in that Country, and have thriven beyond them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. I can ſay little of the <hi>Indians,</hi> but that they are very ſubtil and ingenious, ſeldome or never ſeen upon any occaſion, to expreſſe much joy or ſorrow; the more Eaſtward you go into <hi>New Engl.</hi> the fewer and more effeminat they are; as on the other ſide, the more Weſtward, the more populous, maſculine and marſhall: <hi>yet it was never known, that any of them aſſaulted a Planter upon equall tearms, but wait for a treacherous opportunity, and then make uſe of their advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>20. <hi>I ſhould adviſe thoſe that would undertake to plant new Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies remote from others, to build their houſes ſo neere, that upon all occaſions they may be able to ſecond one another; and for their better ſecuring, to keepe in each houſe a good Maſtiffe Dog, which may give notice of an approaching danger, which otherwiſe would not bee diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and with all are far more terrible to the Indians then either Gun or Sword; alſo I would wiſh all ſuch Planters to entreat the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages fairly, and by no meanes to wrong them for if they be once juſtly exaſperated, they will be found implacable, and will never leave tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing of a reveng until they bring it to execution. Therefore if any one be guilty in that kind, let all the Plantation ſtand upon their guard, and expect no better favour then the</hi> Dutch <hi>received upon</hi> De-la-war Bay. <hi>For the uſe of Fowling pieces, I hould them very neceſſary to ſhoot at</hi> Deere <hi>and Land-fowle, for the</hi> Deere <hi>will be leſſe affrighted with the fall of one that way, then with hunting or courſing at the Herd, and for Land-fowle, the ground is ſo rough, that there is no other means to come by them. But for Sea foule though much ſhooting cannot beat them off the Coaſt, yet they will grow ſo cunning and fearefull, that a man may walk two or 3. houres before he can come to a ſhoot, ſo the beſt courſe is to get into each Plantation a good Fowler that knowes how to lay Nets, and other devices to catch them, who by that means will be better able to furniſh the Planters by his owne labour, then they will with forty Gunnes. There muſt be a good circumspection uſed in civilizing of the Salvages, otherwiſe what will prove their beſt good, may happen the Planters greateſt prejudice; for the meaner ſort of them, they may be trained up any where without any danger, and there bringing up to arts and labour, will prove an aſſiſting help to the Planters. But for the Princes and chiefe of the Country, the ſureſt courſe to prevent trouble and danger, is to ſend them ſo far from the places where they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36057:9"/> were borne, that they may not know what they were, or whence they came, otherwiſe by better understanding what right Princes have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove private men to a Country; and having ſome of the Natives skilled in the Arts and Occupations of the Planters, will perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture thinke themſelves fit and able to reduce the Land people to what wee intended, and ſeeke either by their treacheries ſtrength, or the ayd of other neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Princes, to extirpate the Plantations, and reinveſt themſelves in the poſſeſſion of their ancient Inheritance, which though hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily they cannot effect, would diſtract and diſturbe the Peace of that COUNTRIE.</hi> [<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>]</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:36057:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
